Let's talk about how you can improve
your English. This is another video that
I'm making in which I'm speaking at
normal speed. So, I'm not slowing down.
This is just me talking normally. You
guys really like the last one that I
did. And I'm not going to guarantee that
I'm going to make videos like this all
the time. Like I said before, if you
want my material where I speak at normal
speed or I speak fast, make sure to sign
up for my advanced podcast episodes. Uh
I release a lot of those. And so if you
want regular practice with this, uh
that's your best bet. That's the the
thing you can do to get my material in
which I speak fast. Uh but today I want
to make another video in which I speak
at normal speed like this. And I want to
talk about how you can improve your
English. This is a really broad topic.
This is very vast. There are so many
things that could be said of course. Uh
but I just want to talk about three main
points. I want to talk about three
things that you can focus on that will
help you improve your English and reach
a higher level than what you have right
now. By the way, I'm wearing these
sunglasses again because I'm sitting
outside and it's really cold and I want
to be in the sun and so I'm not just
trying to look cool. Uh I've got these
sunglasses on just so I can record this
in the sun. So, let's talk about uh
three different things you can do in
order to improve your English. And uh
what I want to do is I want to talk
first just about how we improve in any
area because that's really what I'm
going to focus on. Like what three
things do we do in order to improve in
any domain, any skill that we have,
anything that we're trying to improve.
What is it that we need to do? Not just
language learning, but anything in life.
Well, number one, we need repeated
practice so that we can get comfortable
with that thing that we're doing. So,
for example, I think of one of my first
jobs that I had. I worked at a deli. A
deli is a place that sells sandwiches in
the US. And so, uh, I remember making
sandwiches at a deli and that was one of
my first jobs. And the way that I got
better at my job was just doing it
repeatedly. At the very beginning, I was
terrible at making sandwiches. I did not
know what I was doing. And if you've
listened to me talk u in different
episodes of mine uh about this subject,
you know that in general I'm not good
with my hands. Uh, I have a big weakness
when it comes to using my hands to build
things, create things, manipulate
things. I just can't do it well. Uh,
that's always been one of my weaknesses.
And so, you can imagine when I first
started making sandwiches, it took me uh
a while to get the hang of it. But with
repeated practice, I was able to
actually get better at making sandwiches
because I just kept doing it over and
over again. And so, repeated practice,
of course, is necessary if you want to
get better at something, right? Uh the
second thing is that we want to correct
the things that we're doing wrong. Okay?
So you need to identify these things.
You need to see what it is that you're
not doing right and you need to correct
that. Right? Otherwise, you're not going
to improve. In order to improve, you
need to correct the things that you
can't do well, that you're not doing
right. So I can think of another job uh
that I had where I had to fold a lot of
clothes and I had to stack them in a
pile. And uh the only way that I was
able to get better was my manager had to
like take a look and see uh oh, you're
not doing this right or you're not doing
that right. You need to do it more like
this. And that's how I would realize uh
like what my mistakes were. And so I had
to get corrected in order to actually
fold the clothes right, stack them
right. And so if no one had ever told me
that I was wrong about the way I was
doing something, the way I was folding
those clothes, then I wouldn't have
improved. And so, uh, in order to
improve, we want to make sure that we're
correcting the things that we're doing
wrong. And this involves identifying
those things, identifying them and
correcting them, right? And then the
third thing is we need we need to
increase the difficulty of the task that
we're doing in order to actually improve
our skills, right? If you just do the
same thing at the same level, that's not
going to make you um reach a higher
level because you actually have to
practice with things that are at higher
levels than the level that you're at,
right? So, I think of like playing
tennis for example. If you play tennis
against the same level of opponents or
maybe just the same exact opponent who's
just at the same level and you just keep
beating them over and over again, this
isn't going to necessarily make you
reach the next level where you can beat
an opponent who's harder. Uh, in order
to do that, you actually have to
challenge yourself and play harder
opponents and then that'll make you get
better so that can you can actually beat
that opponent, right? And so we need to
increase the difficulty of what we're
doing. All right? So those are the three
things that we need to do, right? We
need to have repeated practice to get
comfortable with what we're doing. We
need to correct the things that we do
wrong. And we need to increase the
difficulty. Those are the three things
that we need to do in order to improve
in any area of life. Okay. So now let's
talk specifically about language
learning. So how can we do those things?
So the first one I mentioned is
repeating, right? Uh repetition. So
repeated practice will help us get
familiar with different words obviously
and phrases and expressions. Uh it'll
help us learn the grammar just
intuitively just by seeing it over and
over again. And it'll help us get
accustomed to the right sounds. Uh we
actually um we could we'll actually
start to hear the correct sounds and be
able to identify them, distinguish them,
get used to them. You'll just get uh
used to how the language actually
sounds, right? and other things as well.
But those are some of the main things
that you can get from repeated practice.
Things that you get comfortable with
when you just repeat uh uh the things
that you're listening to, reading,
saying, whatever it may be. So, repeated
practice is really good. Um, one thing
that I'm doing right now, uh, with
Greek, because I'm learning Greek right
now, is I'm listening to a series of
videos, not just one video, like a
series of videos. There's probably like
50 of them or something like that. Uh
I'm listening to like this series of 50
videos. They're short videos, but I'm
listening to them many times. Like for
example, I think each video I probably
listen to like six, seven times,
sometimes eight times or something like
that. I'm not just doing it over and
over again like the same day. I'm just
talking about like, you know, throughout
um you know, my time listening to these
videos. Over time, I'll revisit these
videos. I'll kind of go in order or I do
it in different ways, but uh I'll end up
uh probably listening to each of these
videos like seven or eight times and
then I'll probably move on. I'm almost
done with that. Uh I've probably
listened to most of them like five or
six times already. And so this might
sound like that's pretty extreme. That's
a lot of repetition. But when you're at
a lower level like I am with Greek, this
is extremely helpful. It's so helpful to
do this type of repeated practice. And
the good thing is that I'm at a low
enough level where it's still just like
thrilling. It's still exciting just to
be able to understand things. So, I
don't get that bored listening to the
same thing again and again because I'm
just happy I understand it. Right? Once
you're at a higher level, it's a little
harder to do this cuz you get bored cuz
you don't have that same thrill of just
like, "Oo, I can understand this." Like,
that's not as exciting anymore. And so
it's a little bit harder to do this
without getting bored when you're at a
higher level. But if you're at a lower
level, this is great, right? This is
like a really, really good way of
learning a bunch of things. Because when
I do this, listening to this content
multiple times, I notice so many things.
Phrases that the person is saying just
stick in my head because I hear them so
much, right? Like I can hear this
person's voice on replay in my head. And
that's really good when you're learning
a language. like hearing their voice,
the person's voice that you're listening
to. That can really help you just kind
of remember phrases and words because
you're kind of remembering the exact
things that they say. And I've gotten
comments from people that say like they
hear my voice uh in their head and when
they read things, they read it in my
voice. And that's a great thing, I
think, because it kind of helps you just
notice things that native speakers say
more. You notice sounds. you notice how
things sound when I say them. So that's
really good. And then um so what else?
So I talked about, you know, listening
to the same thing multiple times like I
do with Greek. Also just frequent
practice. So this isn't exact like uh
repetition. It's not like you're
listening to the same exact thing, but
the fact that you're repeatedly over and
over again doing this type of practice
like you're listening to something like
listening to my different videos or
podcast episodes. uh this frequent
practice, even though it's not literal
repetition, it's repetition in the sense
that you're practicing the same things
over and over again and you're hearing
me say a lot of the same things over and
over again. And so, uh not just literal
repetition, but very frequent practice
of the same type of activity like
listening and reading, speaking, you
know, just doing this a lot is part of
that repetition. So if you're doing a
lot of frequent practice, you're doing a
lot of listening like every day and not
just like a lot in terms of quantity but
frequent like I said. So um you you're
frequently listening, frequently
reading, frequently speaking, frequently
writing. This will help with u just
everything that repetition helps you
with. You'll notice words more. You'll
be able to uh notice different grammar
things intuitively, right? Maybe you
don't even like notice them but inside
you're like absorbing this grammar like
this repeated practice just like with
everything else in our life every other
domain this is a great way uh to improve
your English or any other language that
you're learning. So uh let me move on to
the next point. So correcting your
mistakes. So this is something that
people don't do enough of and that's
because you probably don't have
interaction with a teacher every single
day that's correcting your mistakes. And
so it's understandable that you might
not do that much of this, but it is
something that we should do more of in
order to improve. Okay? Especially if
you're at a level where you can already
understand pretty well and you really
need to focus on your speaking, you're
going to need correction. You're going
to need people to point out to you uh
when you say something that's unnatural,
that's wrong, or whatever. And a lot of
times we can identify this ourselves,
but there are some things that we can't
really identify ourselves. like we need
a native speaker to to show us this. And
so that's why it's actually important to
take classes with native uh speakers or
to just have some kind of contact with
native speakers who can uh do this. And
so uh this will help you identify your
mistakes. So having a tutor that can
help you with your English or whatever
other language that you're learning, uh
this is going to really help you
identify your mistakes. Uh like they
should give you some correction and then
you correct your mistakes. uh in
different ways, right? There's different
ways you can do this. You know, you can
make flashc cards from the different
things that you said wrong. Some people
don't like flash cards. That's okay. You
might just use other forms of uh like
ways to repeat uh this correct phrase
that you said incorrectly. Um you might
try to use it in your own sentences,
writing the uh like sentences down with
these uh with these phrases or these
words that you use wrong or whatever.
So, there's different ways you could do
that. So, uh, tutors, uh, and other
native speakers, uh, are just great, uh,
a great way to do this. Uh, you can do
this without a tutor if you use a
translator and, um, you just like figure
out, uh, what you're saying wrong or
what you're not able to say. So, like I
used to do this a lot in the past where
I would translate my own transcripts
from like my podcast episodes. I would
translate them from English into French
and I would do like writing practice
like that and it would also just help me
uh identify the words and phrases that I
wasn't saying right because I would
check them afterwards with the
translator. Like first I would translate
it and then I would just plug it into
Google Translate and then look at the
difference. Right? So that's a great way
you can do it on your own and it's not
just identifying your mistakes but
you're filling in your gaps. Like some
things you just don't know how to say.
It's not even like a mistake. Like you
just don't know how to say that phrase.
And so you can identify that on your own
using these types of techniques like
what I just said using a translator and
translating things through writing or
speech or whatever. So there are
different ways you can do this. You
know, whether it's a tutor, whether it's
using a translator, there's different
ways you can do this, but you definitely
want to focus on correcting your
mistakes and filling in those gaps of
things that you can't say right. So, um,
especially for those of you that already
understand pretty well and you really
need to focus on your speaking, this is
what you're going to want to do. You're
going to want to correct your mistakes,
identify them, correct them, fill in
your gaps. And this is a surefire way
that you're actually going to improve
because you're going to actually have
more words, you're going to have more
phrases, you're going to have better
grammar or whatever just by correcting
yourself, right? And lastly, you want to
increase your difficulty. Increase the
difficulty of the content that you're
using. Okay? So, you want to listen to
faster English, right? This is an
example of that. So, if you're not used
to this uh speed, it's good that you're
practicing with this because you want to
increase the difficulty of what you're
listening to. You want to listen to
audio instead of video. Video is
actually easier to understand than
audio. So, right now, this is easier
than my advanced episodes. In my
advanced episodes, you don't get to see
me. It's easier when you see me. You see
my hands move. I sometimes make gestures
that kind of help you understand what
I'm saying. If you're just listening to
audio, that's actually more difficult.
That's why it's harder to talk to people
on the phone than it is to talk to them
through a video call, for example. So,
if you understand me here pretty well
right now, well, try my advanced
episodes in which you can't even see me,
and that'll be like, you know, a level
above this, like a slight level. It's
pretty similar, but it's harder when you
can't see me, right? Um, listen to
things that are about harder topics,
right? not just topics about language
learning, but maybe other fields uh
where you're going to be exposed to
harder language, different vocabulary
that you're not familiar with, etc.
Listen to different speakers. I'm going
to be the easiest person for you to
understand probably in English. So, a
way you can increase difficulty is by
listening to other people, not just me.
So, uh a great way you can do that is
with my US Conversations podcast. If you
still want to hear me as part of the
conversation, but you want to hear
someone else speaking as well, you can
use that resource. That link's down
below. Uh, that's a great way for you to
kind of get accustomed to listening to
other people and also listening to more
than one person speaking. I had this
issue when I was learning Spanish is I
would only talk to one person, usually
my wife, and I got really fluent and
comfortable just talking one-on-one. But
then when I moved to Mexico, I realized
that I couldn't function well in groups
where there was more than one person
there because I just couldn't follow
everything they were saying. And then I
had to really practice with this. I had
to get a lot of experience practicing in
group settings where I'm listening to
more than one person. So that's
something that you uh definitely want to
make sure that you're practicing with.
That's another way that you need to
increase the difficulty in order to
reach the next level. So again, you can
use my US Conversations podcast for that
or you can use other content where
there's two people talking and people
that are different and not just me
talking, right? So that'll uh help you
out. But if you need something that's a
little bit uh just a little more
comfortable for you, then of course
check out my US Conversations podcast.
Uh if you already talk to yourself, make
sure you uh start talking to someone
else. That's another way you can
increase the difficulty. You know,
talking to a person is often harder than
just talking to yourself. Uh so that's
something else. Uh writing like if you
already uh do um you know regular
writing practice, write more complicated
texts, write about more complicated
topics, not just what you did on the
weekend, but maybe something else that's
a little more complicated, right?
Describe more complicated things. If you
read, which you should you reading is a
great way to improve your English. If
you read something u or if you read
things in general uh to improve your
English uh if you want to increase the
difficulty read harder things right so
you can do this in you know anything
with your listening you're speaking your
writing your reading you want to make
sure that you're increasing the
difficulty so that you're actually
reaching higher levels okay if you if
you use content that's only at this same
level that's not going to help you reach
the next level okay so those were the
three main points that I wanted to talk
about these help us improve in any area
of life uh but particularly in language
learning as well and so you know it's
general advice but I try to give
specific examples of this and uh
hopefully uh there was something here
that you got that might uh change your
language learning routine or the way
that you're thinking about your progress
in English or whatever other language
that you're learning and me as a con
English content creator who's trying to
help you uh with these three things. Um
I think that you can use my material uh
and you know do these three things that
I just mentioned. And so I try to make
content uh that you can repeat over and
over again like these types of videos
and get that repeated practice. Of
course uh I make uh content uh of
different uh levels of difficulty like
there's my uh easier videos and then
there's like these types of videos.
There's my advanced podcast and there's
my US conversations podcast. So there's
like different, you know, levels of
difficulty you can use uh to increase
the difficulty of the content that
you're listening to or whatever. And
then of course, if you need correction,
you can um take a class with those
different teachers that I talk to on my
US Conversations podcast. And so you can
actually find a teacher there who can
correct your mistakes, uh help you
identify your mistakes. And so even with
that, you know, I have a resource to
kind of help you with that. and you can
find a teacher um from my US
Conversations podcast cuz I mostly talk
to different English teachers from
around the country. So hopefully with my
content you can do these three things
that I mentioned. But in general, if you
find a way to do these three things, you
will improve, your English will improve.
All right, thank you all for watching
this video and I'll talk to you in the
next